<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>NetworkedPlanet</title>
    <description>Experts in Linked and Open Data Publishing</description>
    <link>http://networkedplanet.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://networkedplanet.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 15:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 15:12:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>I see co-producers and stakeholders... everywhere.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blogpost was originally posted on &lt;a href=&quot;http://e-voice.org.uk/twadata/blog/one-entry?entry_id=28325666&quot;&gt;The Way Ahead - Data Theme blog&lt;/a&gt; and is republished here in full&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since our last meeting, Kate and I have been travelling to meetings and events around London. We have much more to do, but we want to update you on the stakeholders/co-producers with which we have engaged and who we hope to engage much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From volunteer sector leaders we learned that funding is often given by charitable people or groups which are not listed as organisations.  We have been asked to try to find ways to include data about these funders, which is seen as a challenge by all, but may become a great project for our data collection and sharing entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have put our vision of the ‘hub’ into a sort of paused-for-additional information state, as we’ve found other organisations which are working toward very similar goals.  These include the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nesta.org.uk/blog/london-office-data-analytics-pilot-now-hard-part&quot;&gt;London Boroughs’ Data Partnership&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.london.gov.uk/dataset/london-office-of-data-analytics&quot;&gt;London Office of Data Analytics&lt;/a&gt;. We hope to speak with the parties involved in leading these efforts soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made contact with local academia, at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://eppi.ioe.ac.uk/cms/&quot;&gt;EPPI-Centre&lt;/a&gt;, and they agree that collaborating makes good sense. Tentatively, in addition to providing links to systematic reviews for use by organisations, we hope to include some brief and helpful tutorials on how to search for and find the right research for whatever project for which one works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have met with the GLA and the London Council, who have helped us identify several needs related to information sharing within the various government offices across the city. They have both been eager to help and be part of collaborating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still want to meet with the engagement officers of as many CCGs as possible, Ipsos Mori (or similar), education data users and providers, and we are reaching out to various communities through a request to the EU National Institutes for Culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will update again! Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 15:17:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2017/01/30/i-see-stakeholders.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2017/01/30/i-see-stakeholders.html</guid>
        
        <category>the way ahead</category>
        
        <category>impact</category>
        
        <category>charities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open Data Camp 4</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Only a few weeks to go! &lt;a href=&quot;http://odcamp.org.uk/announcing-open-data-camp-4/&quot;&gt;Open Data Camp numero 4&lt;/a&gt; is being held at the Pierhead in Cardiff on the Saturday and Sunday, 25-26th of February. ODCamp instantly became my favourite data focused event after I attended the second ODCamp in Manchester and then helped bring it to Bristol for ODCamp3. You can read my &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;other blog posts&lt;/a&gt; if you want to dive deep into my ODCamp journey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since volunteering with the ODCamp organising committee for the Bristol event, I was invited to remain on the organising team to help make future ODCamps happen. I was more than happy to accept and am really delighted to be part of a team made up of such friendly, proactive humans. NetworkedPlanet were proud to be one of the key sponsors of ODCamp3 in Bristol, and remain committed to sponsoring ODCamp4 and future events as we are so impressed with the team’s ability to foster an environment that nurtures forward-thinking ideas and debate surrounding production and consumption of open data in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough of my gushing about the people who run and attend ODCamps - if you’ve not been to one then here’s a quick run down…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;clear:both;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ODCamp is a free &lt;strong&gt;un-&lt;/strong&gt;conference. Unconferences are a particular format of event that doesn’t pre-plan a programme of sessions. Instead, session ideas are “pitched” by the attendees at the start of the day and then, using a show of hands to judge size of space required, pens, and sticky notes, the volunteer crew (called “camp-makers” at ODCamp) create the programme for the day. ODCamp covers costs by offering various sponsorship levels, &lt;a href=&quot;http://odcamp.org.uk/sponsors-feb-2017/&quot;&gt;the list of sponsors helping make ODCamp4 happen is available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp4/odc3_sessionboard.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Creating the  session schedule&quot; height=&quot;426px&quot; width=&quot;640px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my first ODCamp I didn’t plan on pitching a session, but over the course of the first day and chats in the evening afterwards, I realised that a small session on converting CSV data formats to RDF linked data formats might be useful to a few people. I pitched it on the Sunday morning, and that afternoon ran a small workshop messing about with Open Refine to show people how you get from CSV to RDF as basically a “demystifying RDF” workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of ODCamp massively appeals to me because the content is so obviously influenced by the attendees. The organising team have a really good balance of hands-on when it comes to keeping the event flowing and dealing with all the logistics, whilst staying more hands-off to allow the content and discussions to grow organically. Sessions might be round-circle discussions, presentations about tools or projects, building and making of new projects, all kinds of things! You don’t have to pitch a session based on your own subject-knowledge, sessions can be pitched around a question or topic that you want to know more about, and the “pitch” becomes a shout out for other attendees with more knowledge in that area to share in a session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp4/odc3_breakoutspaces.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Break out spaces&quot; height=&quot;426px&quot; width=&quot;640px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest thing is to choose which sessions to go to, you will undoubtedly have 2 or more sessions that you want to attend at the same time. Luckily ODCamp encourages people to move between sessions instead of feeling they must remain for the entirety of one, and this way you can dip in to more than one interesting session (a top tip is to follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/odcamp?src=hash&quot;&gt;live-tweeting&lt;/a&gt; from attendees in other sessions). Some sessions also get covered by the amazing talents at &lt;a href=&quot;https://drawnalism.com/&quot;&gt;Drawnalism&lt;/a&gt;, who live-draw infographics of key points from session content, which are then tacked up around the main room for all to benefit from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp4/odc3_livedrawing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Live drawing capture the key points from sessions&quot; height=&quot;426px&quot; width=&quot;640px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ODCamp releases the free tickets in batches, and each batch “sells out” in a matter of minutes. Those who are unable to attend are &lt;strong&gt;strongly encouraged&lt;/strong&gt; to update their registration so that others can make it in their place. ODCamp4 is already at full capacity but there may well be extra releases if there have been any cancellations, so set your twitter feed to give you notifications from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ODcamp&quot;&gt;@ODCamp&lt;/a&gt; if you’ve not already secured a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve already got a ticket then I’ll see you there, if you miss out this time, ODCamp5 will be along before you know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp4/odc3_finalsession.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open Data Camp - Bristol&quot; height=&quot;426px&quot; width=&quot;640px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All photos used in this post are by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/wnbishop/sets/72157668368192166/&quot;&gt;Nigel Bishop&lt;/a&gt;, licensed &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/&quot;&gt;CC BY-NC 2.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 13:17:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2017/01/30/open-data-camp-4-cardiff.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2017/01/30/open-data-camp-4-cardiff.html</guid>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>unconference</category>
        
        <category>odcamp</category>
        
        <category>events</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Way Ahead for London</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Don’t run.  I am going to write a frightening word, but we can face it together: Co-production.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There. I did it. As an impact evaluator, I often have to help clients find ways to really co-produce data and evaluations, and it is not, often, something that happens without some failures. This can be frightening, because time is always of the essence and because funders want co-production (even when they don’t do it very well).  It is proven to be transformative, though.  It is worth doing and doing well, and it is worth learning from failure at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am endeavouring to practice the things I preach as I work on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lvsc.org.uk/future-of-civil-society-support-in-london-latest-update/work-with-us-to-achieve-the-ambitions-of-the-way-ahead-for-londoners.aspx&quot;&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/a&gt;.  The project seeks to build an infrastructure to help Civil Society organisations, which is as co-produced as possible.  I am only working on the data sharing aspects, but studies have shown that open databases for civil society, which are co-produced, are more used and (assumably) more useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a lot of work to do.  London is a large and very diverse community.  We are going to have to pull our sleeves up and hit the streets, call all partners, think outside the box, and continually look at our stats to see if we are making any headway.  We will also be able to gather information about various communities from digital resources, and we can use scholarship about populations, as well.  The work requires real care, because simply having someone who identifies with a certain group, does not equal having a representative of the group.  We can gather insights from individuals, and then investigate those insights, true, but that is not co-production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-production is a process and a product by which we provide an ongoing method for various stakeholders to be involved in, and provide insight to, research.  The work of co-production often begins by identifying many different stakeholder groups and then finding out how to introduce your project, exhibit listening, and repeat. With each iteration, we gain some insight. Sometimes the new insight is from failure. Such is the nature of learning.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I am part of a large minority in London, an immigrant from America. There are more than 60,000 of us living in London.  Never assume that any opinion I have is anything like any other American, or even like other Americans in London. You will probably be very wrong. No one person can actually speak for large and diverse populations.  BUT, if I tell you that I don’t want to come to your meeting about the data sharing project because I think it is only for people who were born in Britain and have a British accent, then: you have some insight worth investigating.  Are non-UK born people not attending the events because of this perception? Something else? Or is it many things?  By letting other non-UK-born persons know that you have heard the voice of one, you might encourage others to speak up, and then, you may find barriers that inhibit many from a group with a particular situation. (Maybe I am the only one who is intimidated by British accents.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is wonderful and fascinating work, co-producing, and I’ll keep you updated about our strategies and success or failure, here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, I sent out various notices about the meeting in other languages, and I began looking for non-English language radio.  I got a warm reception, which is a good start.  We shall see how it goes.  We’ll also be reaching out to different age groups (and diverse different age groups!), of course, and monitoring involvement by diverse people of various levels of education.  It takes a whole range of people to get this right.  If you want to help, please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;be in touch&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/12/14/the-way-ahead-london.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/12/14/the-way-ahead-london.html</guid>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>impact</category>
        
        <category>charities</category>
        
        <category>the way ahead</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>5 Keys to a Successful Data Strategy for Charities</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This one hour presentation by Lea is aimed at board members, directors, managers and leaders 
of charities, non-profits and social enterprises. Starting with the challenges that these 
organisations face around the collection, processing and use of data; the presentation 
describes the key ways in which leaders can effectively define and implement a data strategy 
and promote evidence informed decision making within their organisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9&quot;&gt;
            &lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GYY9C1DCaO8&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/11/04/successful-data-strategy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/11/04/successful-data-strategy.html</guid>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>impact</category>
        
        <category>charities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Key Data Innovations to Ensure Your Organisation Survives and Thrives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Charity leaders will learn about data protection and how to lead organisations toward better collection and use of data at our workshop at the National Council of Voluntary Organisations in London on the 10th of November. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will review and explore data protection and privacy laws to gain a comfort level that allows participants to lead, wisely, onward, before we delve into new priorities for data collection and use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a true workshop, allowing participants to gain a solid footing on issues that often result in wasted time and energy at charities. The goal is to equip leaders to empower their staff toward the big goals of the organisation - making major gains in efforts to create a better world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/greater-success-for-charities-through-data-innovations-tickets-28288000170&quot; onclick=&quot;trackOutboundLink(&#39;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/greater-success-for-charities-through-data-innovations-tickets-28288000170&#39;); return false;&quot;&gt;Sign Up Via Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/10/24/key-data-innovations.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/10/24/key-data-innovations.html</guid>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>impact</category>
        
        <category>charities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Measuring the Impact of Open Data</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was happy to find widespread agreement about our ideas for the need to measure impact of open data policies, at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatacon.org/&quot;&gt;International Open Data Conference&lt;/a&gt; last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my opinion that we can better guide organisations into a proper data stewardship plan, if we have some way of valuing the various parts of the plan.  I know, some of you are thinking that this will rain on the parade, but measuring the impact of open data policies will not be uneventful.  Wandering into this new field of impact and benefit analysis will be full of excitement and surprises.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first evaluations will begin to answer questions about what is already valuable and what indicators are helpful for determining the value of an open data set.  We won’t be alone in the conversation, and the field won’t stop growing and developing.  Studying the value, though, will help organisations make better decisions and invest more meaningfully in sharing data and learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any thoughts on this? Use the comments section below for further discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/10/11/measuring-the-impact-of-open-data.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/10/11/measuring-the-impact-of-open-data.html</guid>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>impact</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Partners Sought in Data-for-Good Project</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;launching-a-new-series-of-tools-to-help-find-the-solutions-to-the-worlds-problems&quot;&gt;Launching a new series of tools to help find the solutions to the world’s problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;announcement-partners-sought-in-data-for-good-project&quot;&gt;Announcement: Partners Sought in Data-for-Good Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month, NetworkedPlanet has turned a corner. Our company has long managed data, and we are among the vanguard in managing open-linked data, globally.  The world of big data focuses largely on for-profit and consumer insights. We, however, are turning our sights to social problems and the organisations who want to use data-for-good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want to join us?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking for organisations that seek to solve a social, health, or environmental problem, and understand that more data can lead to innovation and insights.  We intend to design bespoke systems to use linkable data from various locations and sectors to provide the cause with a powerful new tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are interested in projects that aim to: relieve suffering; improves the health of the environment; or address disease.  We are especially interested in projects that have more than one sector of interest in terms of data (for example, environmental data and health data, or law enforcement and social data).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will review letters of interest in early November and meet with prospective partners in late November (2016). Meetings may be held via Goto Meeting, if you are based outside of the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be considered, please send a short letter explaining the interests of your organisation, and providing contact details, to: Lea@networkedplanet.com before 29 October 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;networkedplanet-est-buscando-socios-en-el-desarrollo-de-nuevas-herramientas-para-la-investigacin&quot;&gt;NetworkedPlanet está buscando socios en el desarrollo de nuevas herramientas para la investigación.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;queremos-anunciar-un-proyecto-para-utilizar-los-datos-para-buenos-fines-sociales&quot;&gt;Queremos anunciar: Un proyecto para utilizar los datos para buenos fines sociales&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Este mes, NetworkedPlanet (de Gran Bretaña) anuncia una nueva dirección. NetworkedPlanet conseguido datos, y que se encuentran entre la vanguardia en la gestión de los datos ligados y abiertas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mientras que el mundo de los grandes datos se centra principalmente en los conocimientos con fines de lucro y de consumo, nos volvemos nuestra mirada a los problemas sociales y las organizaciones que deseen utilizar los datos para la buena. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;¿Desea Su organización unirse a nosotros? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buscamos a las organizaciones que tratan de resolver un problema del ambiente, de la salud, o la sociedad, y la organización entienden que un mayor número de datos pueden conducir a la innovación y las ideas. Tenemos la intención de diseñar sistemas a medida para utilizar los datos vinculables de varios lugares y sectores para proporcionar la causa con una nueva y poderosa herramienta. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estamos interesados ​​en proyectos que tienen como objetivo: aliviar el sufrimiento; mejora la salud del medio ambiente; o tratar la enfermedad. Estamos especialmente interesados ​​en proyectos que tengan más de un sector de interés en términos de datos (por ejemplo, los datos ambientales y de salud, o por la policía y los datos sociales). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vamos a revisar las cartas de interés a principios de noviembre y se reunirá con los posibles socios a finales de noviembre (2016). Las reuniones podrán ocurer mediante ‘GOTO meeting’ si se basan fuera del Reino Unido. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para ser considerado, por favor envíe una breve carta explicando los intereses de su organización, y con todos los detalles de contacto, a: Lea@networkedplanet.com antes del 29 de octubre de 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/09/21/partners-sought-in-data-for-good-project.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/09/21/partners-sought-in-data-for-good-project.html</guid>
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>data for good</category>
        
        <category>partners</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Proudly sponsoring - How can public data and information support Bristol charities?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many who work in technology are aware of the untapped potential of data to increase the impact of the charity sector. Those who work in voluntary organisations could benefit from this knowledge but are often restricted by resources in what they can achieve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://bristol.theodi.org/&quot;&gt;ODI Bristol&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.voscur.org/&quot;&gt;Voscur&lt;/a&gt; have joined forces to run a workshop to bridge this gap. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re very proud to be sponsoring this event so that these very important conversations can happen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The afternoon workshop will be taking place on &lt;strong&gt;1pm on Thursday 13th October at Hamilton House on Stokes Croft, Bristol&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-center&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom:1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/how-can-public-data-and-information-support-bristol-charities-registration-27213285670&quot;&gt;More Info &amp;amp; Sign Up For Event&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, the Nominet Trust published an in-depth review on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nominettrust.org.uk/knowledge-centre/articles/open-data-and-charities&quot;&gt;“Open Data and Charities”&lt;/a&gt;, setting out to explain the ways in which open data is increasingly coming in to play a role in the charitable sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Existing open government data can be used by charities to add value to their work, to target services better, to improve advocacy and fundraising, and to support knowledge sharing and collaboration between different charities and agencies. Crowdsourcing of open data also offers a new way for charities to gather intelligence, and a wide range of freely available online tools can support charities to analyse open data resources. Realising the potential of open data will require charities to meet a number of technical and organisational challenges. Indeed many charities will need to address key issues relating to open data, whether they choose to pursue benefits from open data or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overcoming the challenges faced by resource-restricted organisations is one of our main concerns at Networked Planet, and we believe that to effectively do this the direction must be set by those who are working in the field. We feel that conversations that start from the ground-up are extremely important in the ongoing conversation about furthering the impact of open data, and are happy to be supporting this event both as a sponsor and also the facilitation of the workshop through Jen’s work in the ODI Bristol steering group.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/09/19/odi-bristol-voscur.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/09/19/odi-bristol-voscur.html</guid>
        
        <category>odi bristol</category>
        
        <category>voscur</category>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>workshop</category>
        
        <category>charities</category>
        
        <category>vcs</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bristol GGD Talk - June 22nd</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Girl Geeks Dinners are monthly events where (predominantly) women meet to network and watch talks over a huge range of tech subjects. When thinking about the best way to present a talk on linked (and open) data, the first thing I thought about was that to do a technical explanation would already be too bamboozling for a mixed crowd. What I needed was to do something more along the lines of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EbpRofMqzF0&quot;&gt;World of Linked Open Data video&lt;/a&gt;. With that in mind, I decided that rather than do a whole hour on the tech of linked and open data, I’d ask along some local data heroes. After first doing a #101 style talk about what linked and open data is, I’ll introduce &lt;strong&gt;Martha King&lt;/strong&gt;, who’s doing incredibly interesting work at Knowle West Media centre. There they have been investigating how tech and data can improve the lives of those who live here in Bristol by making use of sensor technology. Finishing up the talks will be &lt;strong&gt;Katherine Rooney&lt;/strong&gt;, project manager for the open data efforts of Connecting Bristol at Bristol City Council. She’ll be talking about the various projects that are already going on in Bristol and also explaining what the local &lt;a href=&quot;https://theodi.org/nodes&quot;&gt;ODI Node&lt;/a&gt; is doing and how to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the talks (each only around 15 mins), we’ll have space for a Q&amp;amp;A session before the usual community notices and chatting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the details you need are on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bristol.girlgeekdinners.com/2016/05/17/ggd52-the-world-of-linked-open-data/&quot;&gt;Bristol Girl Geeks’ website&lt;/a&gt; and you can sign up (spaces are limited) on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Bristol-Girl-Geek-Dinners/events/231193829/&quot;&gt;BGGD Meetup.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/05/18/bristol-girl-geek-dinner.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/05/18/bristol-girl-geek-dinner.html</guid>
        
        <category>linked data</category>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>talk</category>
        
        <category>networking</category>
        
        <category>girl geeks</category>
        
        <category>bristol</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open Data Camp 3 - Bristol fashion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year I blogged about just how &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2015/10/13/open-data-camp.html&quot;&gt;impressed I was with Open Data Camp 2&lt;/a&gt;, a free unconference that was held in Manchester. The &lt;strong&gt;un-&lt;/strong&gt;conference format of Open Data Camp (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23odcamp&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;#odcamp&lt;/a&gt; as you’ll find people hashtagging) means that each day starts with attendees pitching suggestions for topics, which are then organised into a day incredibly interesting sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of ODCamp2, there was a call out for suggestions for host volunteers and I quickly started working on a two-pronged attack that consisted largely of pestering the ODCamp organisers and also doing a lot of arm-waving back in Bristol to enthuse about what was so great about ODCamp itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;local-heroes&quot;&gt;Local heroes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for us, there’s an active data geek group in Bristol in the form of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/south-west-data/&quot;&gt;South West Data&lt;/a&gt; who were instrumental in securing the amazing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.watershed.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Watershed&lt;/a&gt; as the venue, and through chats at the South West Data meetups,  Bristol City Council’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.connectingbristol.org/&quot;&gt;Connecting Bristol&lt;/a&gt; got on board with crucial support and sponsorship early on too. ODCamp makes use of several break-out spaces for sessions, and so again we were really lucky to have the support of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.watershed.co.uk/pmstudio/&quot;&gt;Pervasive Media Studios&lt;/a&gt;, who allowed us to use their neighbouring meeting spaces next door to the Watershed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a big hat-tip to &lt;strong&gt;Katherine Rooney&lt;/strong&gt; (Connecting Bristol), &lt;strong&gt;Kev Kirkland&lt;/strong&gt; (Data Unity, SWData organiser &amp;amp; resident at Pervasive Media Studios), &lt;strong&gt;Simon Price&lt;/strong&gt; (University of Bristol &amp;amp; SWData organiser) and &lt;strong&gt;Angharad Stone&lt;/strong&gt; (Environment Agency) without whose help ODCamp3 may have never made it to Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-weekend-in-brief&quot;&gt;The weekend in brief&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could wax lyrical about the content of ODCamp - but instead I’ll direct you to this &lt;a href=&quot;https://storify.com/RnROrganisation/open-data-camp-3-mostly-in-pics&quot;&gt;storify of the weekend&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rnrorganisation.co.uk/&quot;&gt;RnR Organisation&lt;/a&gt; - it gives a great overview of what you miss out on when you miss an ODCamp!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://drawnalism.com/&quot;&gt;Drawnalism&lt;/a&gt; was in attendance again, this time with two illustrators &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; two live-bloggers. You can see the results of the blogging over on &lt;a href=&quot;http://odcamp.org.uk&quot;&gt;odcamp.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; as well as the illustrations, but I’ll pull a few here to give you a taster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp3/OpenDataForNewbies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open Data For Newbies - Drawnalism illustration of session content&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp3/ODCamp-Day-Two_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Beyond the Hack - Drawnalism illustration of session content&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp3/New-Doc-12_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Data Platform Requirements - Drawnalism illustration of session content&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the ODCamp website for links to more blog posts from attendees, session notes taken throughout the meetings, live blogs and illustrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;odcamp-4&quot;&gt;ODCamp 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t stress enough how enjoyable it is to attend an ODCamp, the organisers have the perfect balance of hands-on to keep things moving and sessions on track, and hands-off enough to allow the conference to be built by the people, for the people. Please do sign up for updates and make sure you’re following all the usual channels to hear where and when the next ODCamp will be held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like ODcamp to come to your city, here’s my 3 top tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find a potential local venue. It needs to be accessible (no stairs without lifts etc), fairly easy to get to from the local public transport hub (train/bus station) and has a main room that can hold around 60-80 people, with 4 or so smaller break-out spaces that hold 15-20 people (varying sizes are OK)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enlist the support of other local meet up groups. It’s really difficult to do everything without other local enthusiasts - connect with people and team up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let the ODCamp organisers know that you’re out trying to find venues and people, if they’re in the dark the next location might get decided while you’re out building support!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;until-next-time&quot;&gt;Until next time!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more on ODCamp, do check out their website and twitter. We’re &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; much looking forward to the next one, wherever that may be! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/05/17/odcamp3-bristol.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/05/17/odcamp3-bristol.html</guid>
        
        <category>linked data</category>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>conference</category>
        
        <category>odcamp</category>
        
        <category>events</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
