<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>NetworkedPlanet</title>
    <description>Experts in Linked and Open Data Publishing</description>
    <link>http://networkedplanet.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://networkedplanet.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 11:10:18 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 11:10:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>5 Keys to a Successful Data Strategy for Charities</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This one hour presentation by Lea is aimed at board members, directors, managers and leaders of charities, non-profits and social enterprises. Starting with the challenges that these organisations face around the collection, processing and use of data; the presentation describes the key ways in which leaders can effectively define and implement a data strategy and promote evidence informed decision making within their organisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video is also a useful introduction to concepts that we will delve into in much more detail in our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/10/24/key-data-innovations.html&quot;&gt;forthcoming workshop&lt;/a&gt; at the National Council of Voluntary Organisations in London on the 10th of November. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; id=&quot;row-3&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 col-md-offset-3&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9&quot;&gt;
			&lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GYY9C1DCaO8&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/11/04/successful-data-strategy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/11/04/successful-data-strategy.html</guid>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>impact</category>
        
        <category>charities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Key Data Innovations to Ensure Your Organisation Survives and Thrives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Charity leaders will learn about data protection and how to lead organisations toward better collection and use of data at our workshop at the National Council of Voluntary Organisations in London on the 10th of November. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will review and explore data protection and privacy laws to gain a comfort level that allows participants to lead, wisely, onward, before we delve into new priorities for data collection and use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a true workshop, allowing participants to gain a solid footing on issues that often result in wasted time and energy at charities. The goal is to equip leaders to empower their staff toward the big goals of the organisation - making major gains in efforts to create a better world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/greater-success-for-charities-through-data-innovations-tickets-28288000170&quot; onclick=&quot;trackOutboundLink(&#39;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/greater-success-for-charities-through-data-innovations-tickets-28288000170&#39;); return false;&quot;&gt;Sign Up Via Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/10/24/key-data-innovations.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/10/24/key-data-innovations.html</guid>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>impact</category>
        
        <category>charities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Measuring the Impact of Open Data</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was happy to find widespread agreement about our ideas for the need to measure impact of open data policies, at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatacon.org/&quot;&gt;International Open Data Conference&lt;/a&gt; last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my opinion that we can better guide organisations into a proper data stewardship plan, if we have some way of valuing the various parts of the plan.  I know, some of you are thinking that this will rain on the parade, but measuring the impact of open data policies will not be uneventful.  Wandering into this new field of impact and benefit analysis will be full of excitement and surprises.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first evaluations will begin to answer questions about what is already valuable and what indicators are helpful for determining the value of an open data set.  We won’t be alone in the conversation, and the field won’t stop growing and developing.  Studying the value, though, will help organisations make better decisions and invest more meaningfully in sharing data and learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any thoughts on this? Use the comments section below for further discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/10/11/measuring-the-impact-of-open-data.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/10/11/measuring-the-impact-of-open-data.html</guid>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>impact</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Partners Sought in Data-for-Good Project</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;launching-a-new-series-of-tools-to-help-find-the-solutions-to-the-worlds-problems&quot;&gt;Launching a new series of tools to help find the solutions to the world’s problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;announcement-partners-sought-in-data-for-good-project&quot;&gt;Announcement: Partners Sought in Data-for-Good Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month, NetworkedPlanet has turned a corner. Our company has long managed data, and we are among the vanguard in managing open-linked data, globally.  The world of big data focuses largely on for-profit and consumer insights. We, however, are turning our sights to social problems and the organisations who want to use data-for-good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want to join us?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking for organisations that seek to solve a social, health, or environmental problem, and understand that more data can lead to innovation and insights.  We intend to design bespoke systems to use linkable data from various locations and sectors to provide the cause with a powerful new tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are interested in projects that aim to: relieve suffering; improves the health of the environment; or address disease.  We are especially interested in projects that have more than one sector of interest in terms of data (for example, environmental data and health data, or law enforcement and social data).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will review letters of interest in early November and meet with prospective partners in late November (2016). Meetings may be held via Goto Meeting, if you are based outside of the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be considered, please send a short letter explaining the interests of your organisation, and providing contact details, to: Lea@networkedplanet.com before 29 October 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;networkedplanet-est-buscando-socios-en-el-desarrollo-de-nuevas-herramientas-para-la-investigacin&quot;&gt;NetworkedPlanet está buscando socios en el desarrollo de nuevas herramientas para la investigación.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;queremos-anunciar-un-proyecto-para-utilizar-los-datos-para-buenos-fines-sociales&quot;&gt;Queremos anunciar: Un proyecto para utilizar los datos para buenos fines sociales&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Este mes, NetworkedPlanet (de Gran Bretaña) anuncia una nueva dirección. NetworkedPlanet conseguido datos, y que se encuentran entre la vanguardia en la gestión de los datos ligados y abiertas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mientras que el mundo de los grandes datos se centra principalmente en los conocimientos con fines de lucro y de consumo, nos volvemos nuestra mirada a los problemas sociales y las organizaciones que deseen utilizar los datos para la buena. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;¿Desea Su organización unirse a nosotros? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buscamos a las organizaciones que tratan de resolver un problema del ambiente, de la salud, o la sociedad, y la organización entienden que un mayor número de datos pueden conducir a la innovación y las ideas. Tenemos la intención de diseñar sistemas a medida para utilizar los datos vinculables de varios lugares y sectores para proporcionar la causa con una nueva y poderosa herramienta. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estamos interesados ​​en proyectos que tienen como objetivo: aliviar el sufrimiento; mejora la salud del medio ambiente; o tratar la enfermedad. Estamos especialmente interesados ​​en proyectos que tengan más de un sector de interés en términos de datos (por ejemplo, los datos ambientales y de salud, o por la policía y los datos sociales). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vamos a revisar las cartas de interés a principios de noviembre y se reunirá con los posibles socios a finales de noviembre (2016). Las reuniones podrán ocurer mediante ‘GOTO meeting’ si se basan fuera del Reino Unido. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para ser considerado, por favor envíe una breve carta explicando los intereses de su organización, y con todos los detalles de contacto, a: Lea@networkedplanet.com antes del 29 de octubre de 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/09/21/partners-sought-in-data-for-good-project.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/09/21/partners-sought-in-data-for-good-project.html</guid>
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>data for good</category>
        
        <category>partners</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Proudly sponsoring - How can public data and information support Bristol charities?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many who work in technology are aware of the untapped potential of data to increase the impact of the charity sector. Those who work in voluntary organisations could benefit from this knowledge but are often restricted by resources in what they can achieve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://bristol.theodi.org/&quot;&gt;ODI Bristol&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.voscur.org/&quot;&gt;Voscur&lt;/a&gt; have joined forces to run a workshop to bridge this gap. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re very proud to be sponsoring this event so that these very important conversations can happen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The afternoon workshop will be taking place on &lt;strong&gt;1pm on Thursday 13th October at Hamilton House on Stokes Croft, Bristol&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-center&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom:1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/how-can-public-data-and-information-support-bristol-charities-registration-27213285670&quot;&gt;More Info &amp;amp; Sign Up For Event&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, the Nominet Trust published an in-depth review on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nominettrust.org.uk/knowledge-centre/articles/open-data-and-charities&quot;&gt;“Open Data and Charities”&lt;/a&gt;, setting out to explain the ways in which open data is increasingly coming in to play a role in the charitable sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Existing open government data can be used by charities to add value to their work, to target services better, to improve advocacy and fundraising, and to support knowledge sharing and collaboration between different charities and agencies. Crowdsourcing of open data also offers a new way for charities to gather intelligence, and a wide range of freely available online tools can support charities to analyse open data resources. Realising the potential of open data will require charities to meet a number of technical and organisational challenges. Indeed many charities will need to address key issues relating to open data, whether they choose to pursue benefits from open data or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overcoming the challenges faced by resource-restricted organisations is one of our main concerns at Networked Planet, and we believe that to effectively do this the direction must be set by those who are working in the field. We feel that conversations that start from the ground-up are extremely important in the ongoing conversation about furthering the impact of open data, and are happy to be supporting this event both as a sponsor and also the facilitation of the workshop through Jen’s work in the ODI Bristol steering group.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/09/19/odi-bristol-voscur.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/09/19/odi-bristol-voscur.html</guid>
        
        <category>odi bristol</category>
        
        <category>voscur</category>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>workshop</category>
        
        <category>charities</category>
        
        <category>vcs</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bristol GGD Talk - June 22nd</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Girl Geeks Dinners are monthly events where (predominantly) women meet to network and watch talks over a huge range of tech subjects. When thinking about the best way to present a talk on linked (and open) data, the first thing I thought about was that to do a technical explanation would already be too bamboozling for a mixed crowd. What I needed was to do something more along the lines of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EbpRofMqzF0&quot;&gt;World of Linked Open Data video&lt;/a&gt;. With that in mind, I decided that rather than do a whole hour on the tech of linked and open data, I’d ask along some local data heroes. After first doing a #101 style talk about what linked and open data is, I’ll introduce &lt;strong&gt;Martha King&lt;/strong&gt;, who’s doing incredibly interesting work at Knowle West Media centre. There they have been investigating how tech and data can improve the lives of those who live here in Bristol by making use of sensor technology. Finishing up the talks will be &lt;strong&gt;Katherine Rooney&lt;/strong&gt;, project manager for the open data efforts of Connecting Bristol at Bristol City Council. She’ll be talking about the various projects that are already going on in Bristol and also explaining what the local &lt;a href=&quot;https://theodi.org/nodes&quot;&gt;ODI Node&lt;/a&gt; is doing and how to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the talks (each only around 15 mins), we’ll have space for a Q&amp;amp;A session before the usual community notices and chatting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the details you need are on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bristol.girlgeekdinners.com/2016/05/17/ggd52-the-world-of-linked-open-data/&quot;&gt;Bristol Girl Geeks’ website&lt;/a&gt; and you can sign up (spaces are limited) on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Bristol-Girl-Geek-Dinners/events/231193829/&quot;&gt;BGGD Meetup.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/05/18/bristol-girl-geek-dinner.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/05/18/bristol-girl-geek-dinner.html</guid>
        
        <category>linked data</category>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>talk</category>
        
        <category>networking</category>
        
        <category>girl geeks</category>
        
        <category>bristol</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open Data Camp 3 - Bristol fashion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year I blogged about just how &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2015/10/13/open-data-camp.html&quot;&gt;impressed I was with Open Data Camp 2&lt;/a&gt;, a free unconference that was held in Manchester. The &lt;strong&gt;un-&lt;/strong&gt;conference format of Open Data Camp (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23odcamp&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;#odcamp&lt;/a&gt; as you’ll find people hashtagging) means that each day starts with attendees pitching suggestions for topics, which are then organised into a day incredibly interesting sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of ODCamp2, there was a call out for suggestions for host volunteers and I quickly started working on a two-pronged attack that consisted largely of pestering the ODCamp organisers and also doing a lot of arm-waving back in Bristol to enthuse about what was so great about ODCamp itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;local-heroes&quot;&gt;Local heroes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for us, there’s an active data geek group in Bristol in the form of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/south-west-data/&quot;&gt;South West Data&lt;/a&gt; who were instrumental in securing the amazing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.watershed.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Watershed&lt;/a&gt; as the venue, and through chats at the South West Data meetups,  Bristol City Council’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.connectingbristol.org/&quot;&gt;Connecting Bristol&lt;/a&gt; got on board with crucial support and sponsorship early on too. ODCamp makes use of several break-out spaces for sessions, and so again we were really lucky to have the support of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.watershed.co.uk/pmstudio/&quot;&gt;Pervasive Media Studios&lt;/a&gt;, who allowed us to use their neighbouring meeting spaces next door to the Watershed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a big hat-tip to &lt;strong&gt;Katherine Rooney&lt;/strong&gt; (Connecting Bristol), &lt;strong&gt;Kev Kirkland&lt;/strong&gt; (Data Unity, SWData organiser &amp;amp; resident at Pervasive Media Studios), &lt;strong&gt;Simon Price&lt;/strong&gt; (University of Bristol &amp;amp; SWData organiser) and &lt;strong&gt;Angharad Stone&lt;/strong&gt; (Environment Agency) without whose help ODCamp3 may have never made it to Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-weekend-in-brief&quot;&gt;The weekend in brief&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could wax lyrical about the content of ODCamp - but instead I’ll direct you to this &lt;a href=&quot;https://storify.com/RnROrganisation/open-data-camp-3-mostly-in-pics&quot;&gt;storify of the weekend&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rnrorganisation.co.uk/&quot;&gt;RnR Organisation&lt;/a&gt; - it gives a great overview of what you miss out on when you miss an ODCamp!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://drawnalism.com/&quot;&gt;Drawnalism&lt;/a&gt; was in attendance again, this time with two illustrators &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; two live-bloggers. You can see the results of the blogging over on &lt;a href=&quot;http://odcamp.org.uk&quot;&gt;odcamp.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; as well as the illustrations, but I’ll pull a few here to give you a taster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp3/OpenDataForNewbies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open Data For Newbies - Drawnalism illustration of session content&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp3/ODCamp-Day-Two_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Beyond the Hack - Drawnalism illustration of session content&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/odcamp3/New-Doc-12_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Data Platform Requirements - Drawnalism illustration of session content&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the ODCamp website for links to more blog posts from attendees, session notes taken throughout the meetings, live blogs and illustrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;odcamp-4&quot;&gt;ODCamp 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t stress enough how enjoyable it is to attend an ODCamp, the organisers have the perfect balance of hands-on to keep things moving and sessions on track, and hands-off enough to allow the conference to be built by the people, for the people. Please do sign up for updates and make sure you’re following all the usual channels to hear where and when the next ODCamp will be held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like ODcamp to come to your city, here’s my 3 top tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find a potential local venue. It needs to be accessible (no stairs without lifts etc), fairly easy to get to from the local public transport hub (train/bus station) and has a main room that can hold around 60-80 people, with 4 or so smaller break-out spaces that hold 15-20 people (varying sizes are OK)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enlist the support of other local meet up groups. It’s really difficult to do everything without other local enthusiasts - connect with people and team up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let the ODCamp organisers know that you’re out trying to find venues and people, if they’re in the dark the next location might get decided while you’re out building support!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;until-next-time&quot;&gt;Until next time!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more on ODCamp, do check out their website and twitter. We’re &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; much looking forward to the next one, wherever that may be! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/05/17/odcamp3-bristol.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/05/17/odcamp3-bristol.html</guid>
        
        <category>linked data</category>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>conference</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Newsletter Issue 3 hits the inboxes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The third issue of our email newsletter has hit the &lt;a href=&quot;http://networkedplanet.us11.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=62daac7ae19a90ef03ea3bd42&amp;amp;id=a797a2dd15&quot;&gt;mailing list&lt;/a&gt; inboxes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://us11.campaign-archive1.com/?u=62daac7ae19a90ef03ea3bd42&amp;amp;id=e7d12c0b8a&quot;&gt;Click here to read this issue&lt;/a&gt; in your browser, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://us11.campaign-archive1.com/home/?u=62daac7ae19a90ef03ea3bd42&amp;amp;id=a797a2dd15&quot;&gt;access the newsletter archive here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://networkedplanet.us11.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=62daac7ae19a90ef03ea3bd42&amp;amp;id=a797a2dd15&quot;&gt;Sign up to our mailing list&lt;/a&gt; - we send newsletters roughly quarterly, possibly punctuated with the odd single-shot news item if we think it’s important!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/03/29/newsletter-issue-3.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/03/29/newsletter-issue-3.html</guid>
        
        <category>newsletter</category>
        
        <category>mailing list</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open data feedback at work!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whilst finishing off my article on &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/02/29/linked-data-101-querying.html&quot;&gt;querying linked data&lt;/a&gt;, I decided it would be nice to end with something a little more tangible than simply another SPARQL query. I decided a nice map showing the data that I’d converted from CSV to RDF would do the trick. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst it was quick work to display a map using OpenStreetMap tiles and Leaflet.js, something was peculiar - the map markers were nowhere to be seen, and scrolling out found them off the coast of Somalia! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/datafix/badmap.png&quot; alt=&quot;London allotments in the seas off the coast of Somalia&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;These allotments would have problems with damp&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started tracing back through my steps and found the culprit in the original CSV file - the headings had been mixed up for the longitude and latitude. I headed back to the London Datastore to double check and yes, that was the way in which the data had been published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clicking over to their contact page I quickly fired off an e-mail to let them know of the error, and in the matter of a mere &lt;strong&gt;20 minutes&lt;/strong&gt; I had received an email back saying that the data had been fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/datafix/goodmap.png&quot; alt=&quot;London allotments in Walthamstow&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;That’s more like it!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very easy to let simple errors slip by, I know what ranges UK latitudes and longitudes should be and I didn’t spot it even though the &lt;a href=&quot;http://levelup.networkedplanet.com/&quot;&gt;Level Up converter&lt;/a&gt; shows a preview of the original CSV. When working with lots and lots of values it’s easy for things like this to get through and it was the mapping visualisation that made it obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s really great is it also shows another benefit of open data, the community aspect of keeping your raw data error-free. Each user of an open dataset has a vested interest in that data being correct. In my case, I wanted it to be able to demonstrate a conversion to RDF, but it could &lt;em&gt;easily&lt;/em&gt; be developers or users of an app that use your data in their offerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a massive shout out to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LDN_data&quot; title=&quot;London Datastore Twitter&quot;&gt;@ldn_data&lt;/a&gt; for their super fast response in getting the data sorted!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gifrific.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/Tina-Fey-giving-herself-high-five.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Gif: liz lemon high five&quot; width=&quot;350px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center img-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;You rock!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/03/01/open-data-feedback-at-work.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/03/01/open-data-feedback-at-work.html</guid>
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Linked Data 101 - Querying data with SPARQL</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;well text-center&quot;&gt;This article is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tags/ld101-series/&quot;&gt;Linked Data 101 series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;previously&quot;&gt;Previously…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far in the Linked Data 101 series, we looked first at &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/02/16/linked-data-101-identifiers.html&quot;&gt;why we use URIs as identifiers&lt;/a&gt;, and then moved on to looking at &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/02/17/linked-data-101-predicates.html&quot;&gt;predicates&lt;/a&gt; in the second article. The third article had a walk-through of taking CSV data and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/02/18/linked-data-101-making-data-linkable-tutorial.html&quot;&gt;using Level Up online CSV to RDF converter&lt;/a&gt; to structure the data ready for the Web of Data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve got some RDF from Level Up, I’ll show you how to get started with some simple queries on that data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brightstardb&quot;&gt;BrightstarDB&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various RDF data stores available for different platforms and with various offerings in terms of management tools. For the purpose of this article I’m going to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://brightstardb.com/&quot;&gt;BrightstarDB&lt;/a&gt; as it’s a native .NET triple store (and cross-platform friendly), it’s open source, and also it’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://networkedplanet.com/#products&quot;&gt;ours&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing BrightstarDB is very simple, grab the &lt;a href=&quot;http://brightstardb.codeplex.com/&quot;&gt;latest release&lt;/a&gt; and then fire up the installer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-install2.png&quot; alt=&quot;BrightstarDB installation&quot; width=&quot;550px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alert alert-info text-center&quot;&gt;Full documentation about installing and developing with BrightstarDB as well as using Polaris, is available online at &lt;a href=&quot;http://brightstardb.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;BrightstarDB documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;polaris&quot;&gt;Polaris&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-icon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Polaris icon&quot; width=&quot;120px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive pull-left gap-right-dbl gap-bottom bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polaris is a Windows desktop application that allows a user to manage various aspects of local and remote BrightstarDB servers. Using Polaris you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create and delete stores on the server&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Import N-Triples or N-Quads files into a store&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run a SPARQL query against a store&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run an update transaction against a store&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;clear:both;&quot;&gt;We’re going to concentrate on creating a store, importing our triples and then doing simple queries on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;create-a-connection&quot;&gt;Create a connection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can use different protocols - Embedded and REST - for connecting to the BrightstarDB server now installed on our machine. We’re going to use the embedded protocol*:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select File &amp;gt; New Connection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter “Embedded” as the Connection Name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select “Embedded” as the Connection Type&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select a file path to use as the stores directory**&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click OK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* If you prefer to run the BrightstarDB service a different way, you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://brightstardb.readthedocs.org/en/latest/Running_BrightstarDB/#&quot;&gt;read more in the documentation here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** Make sure you have enough security access rights to read and write to that location&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;create-a-data-store&quot;&gt;Create a data store&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a data store select the new &lt;em&gt;“Embedded”&lt;/em&gt; connection and select Server &amp;gt; New Store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-newstore.png&quot; alt=&quot;Create a data store in Polaris&quot; width=&quot;550px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Store Name field is pre-filled with a randomly generated name, so let’s change it to something more memorable - &lt;em&gt;Allotments&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we’re going to take the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/02/18/linked-data-101-making-data-linkable-tutorial.html&quot;&gt;RDF data produced in the last article&lt;/a&gt; (a download is available on that page) and upload it to our store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;importing-data&quot;&gt;Importing data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we’ve got BrightstarDB installed on our local machine, we’re going to run a Local Import (there are &lt;a href=&quot;http://brightstardb.readthedocs.org/en/latest/Using_Polaris/#importing-data&quot;&gt;more options for importing data&lt;/a&gt; depending on your server set up).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unzip the data download produced by the Level Up converter. This gives you the same data in three different formats - N-Triples, RDF-XML and Turtle. Polaris can import any of these formats (along with N-Quads, RDF/JSON and Notation3), so I’m choosing to import the N-Triples file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select the &lt;em&gt;Allotments&lt;/em&gt; store from the connections list, then choose Store &amp;gt; New &amp;gt; Import Job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re not concerned about specific graph names at this point so we simply select our N-Triples file using the file explorer dialog and click Start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-import.png&quot; alt=&quot;Import data using Polaris&quot; width=&quot;550px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alert alert-info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Local import is not recommended for large data files. If the file you try to import exceeds 50MB in size a warning will be displayed. &lt;a href=&quot;http://brightstardb.readthedocs.org/en/latest/Using_Polaris/#importing-data&quot;&gt;Read more information in the docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;select-all&quot;&gt;Select All&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first query we’re going to do is a simple “Select All” so that we can view all the triples in Polaris. Right-click the &lt;em&gt;“Allotments”&lt;/em&gt; store and select New &amp;gt; SPARQL query.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the query below in the Query field and then press F5 (or hit the “Run” icon button)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;SELECT *
WHERE
{ ?s ?p ?o }&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-selectall1.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Select All query&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve chosen &lt;code&gt;?s&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;?p&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;?o&lt;/code&gt; for my variable names for the three parts of the triples - subject, predicate and object - you may choose to use different variable names. For example the below is the exact same query:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;SELECT *
WHERE
{ ?id ?property ?value }&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flipping the tabs we can view the data in a results table or an XML view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-selectall2.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Select All results table&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-selectall3.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Select All results XML&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;query-all-triples-for-a-particular-resource&quot;&gt;Query: all triples for a particular resource&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To view all the triples for a particular resource, we enter its identifier into the query, like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;SELECT *
WHERE
{ &amp;lt;http://data.contoso.com/environment/allotments/358&amp;gt; ?p ?o }&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is similar to saying “Get me all the predicates and objects that have this identifier as their subject.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-filter-id.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Get triples for a particular resource&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;query-all-resources-using-a-particular-predicate&quot;&gt;Query: all resources using a particular predicate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we can view all the resources that use a particular predicate and their values by entering the query below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
SELECT *
WHERE
{ ?s &amp;lt;http://data.contoso.com/environment/ontology/facilities&amp;gt; ?o }
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-filter-pred.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Get triples for a particular predicate&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, not all resources had properties using this predicate and so only 18 results are returned - showing the subject and object parts of the triples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;query-all-resources-using-a-particular-value&quot;&gt;Query: all resources using a particular value&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look up some resources that have entered a certain value as the object of their “supplied postcode” triple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
SELECT *
WHERE
{ ?s &amp;lt;http://data.contoso.com/environment/ontology/suppliedPostcode&amp;gt; &quot;E17&quot; }
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-filter-val1.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Get triples using a particular value&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings back 12 records, but as you can see we only have their identifiers (the predicate and object part of the triples have been supplied in the query), in order to return more information about those resources we need to ask for more in the query.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
SELECT *
WHERE
{ 
?s &amp;lt;http://data.contoso.com/environment/ontology/suppliedPostcode&amp;gt; &quot;E17&quot; .
?s ?p ?o
}
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first line of our query retrieves subjects using “E17” with the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://data.contoso.com/environment/ontology/suppliedPostcode&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; predicate, and the second retrieves all triples that link to those subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-filter-val2.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Get triples using a particular value&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we don’t want &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the triples associated with the given subjects, but instead want to simply return one other value - we can modify the query like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
SELECT *
WHERE
{ 
?s &amp;lt;http://data.contoso.com/environment/ontology/suppliedPostcode&amp;gt; &quot;E17&quot; .
?s &amp;lt;http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label&amp;gt; ?o .
}
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-filter-val3.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Get triples using a particular value&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ordering-results&quot;&gt;Ordering results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can order those results by using the &lt;code&gt;ORDER BY&lt;/code&gt; phrase:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
SELECT *
WHERE
{ 
?s &amp;lt;http://data.contoso.com/environment/ontology/suppliedPostcode&amp;gt; &quot;E17&quot; .
?s &amp;lt;http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label&amp;gt; ?label .
}
ORDER BY ?label
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-order.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Order by&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;limiting-the-number-returned&quot;&gt;Limiting the number returned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only want the top 5? We simply add a &lt;code&gt;LIMIT&lt;/code&gt; phrase to the SPARQL statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
SELECT *
WHERE
{ 
?s &amp;lt;http://data.contoso.com/environment/ontology/suppliedPostcode&amp;gt; &quot;E17&quot; .
?s &amp;lt;http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label&amp;gt; ?label .
}
ORDER BY ?label
LIMIT 5
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-limit.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Limit the number of results returned&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;only-returning-particular-values&quot;&gt;Only returning particular values&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we only want or need particular values, we can replace the &lt;code&gt;SELECT *&lt;/code&gt; and be more specific:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
SELECT ?label ?long ?lat
WHERE
{ 
?s &amp;lt;http://data.contoso.com/environment/ontology/suppliedPostcode&amp;gt; &quot;E17&quot; .
?s &amp;lt;http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label&amp;gt; ?label .
?s &amp;lt;http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#lat&amp;gt; ?lat . 
?s &amp;lt;http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#long&amp;gt; ?long . 
}
ORDER BY ?label
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/linkeddata101/pol-values.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPARQL Select which values to include&quot; width=&quot;750px&quot; class=&quot;img-medium img-responsive center-block bordered-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-use-of-the-data&quot;&gt;Making use of the data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see by the returned values how easily they can be visualised. Using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openstreetmap.org/&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; (a free editable map of the world available as open data) and the open source &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com&quot;&gt;Leaflet.js&lt;/a&gt; we can quickly place the pinpoints to view on a map using the javascript code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;map&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
var markers = [
    {&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Cheshire Fields&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.038715, &quot;lat&quot;:51.576236},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Chestnuts Farm&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.014994, &quot;lat&quot;:51.592189},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Forest Road&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:0.005339, &quot;lat&quot;:51.591496},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Hale End Road&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.000226, &quot;lat&quot;:51.596406},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Higham Hill Common&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.02978, &quot;lat&quot;:51.593777},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Honeybone&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.033135, &quot;lat&quot;:51.577039},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Low Hall Farm&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.033687, &quot;lat&quot;:51.571343},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Low Hall Lane&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.032928, &quot;lat&quot;:51.576619},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Markhouse Common&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.026112, &quot;lat&quot;:51.576161},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Sinnott Road&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.041737, &quot;lat&quot;:51.598899},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Trencherfield&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.040005, &quot;lat&quot;:51.596741},
	{&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Willow Tree&quot;, &quot;long&quot;:-0.018091, &quot;lat&quot;:51.605109}
];

var map = L.map(&#39;map&#39;).setView([51.58693, -0.04], 12);

var tiles = L.tileLayer(&#39;http://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png&#39;, {
	maxZoom: 19,
	attribution: &#39;&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/copyright&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;&#39;
}).addTo(map);

for(var i = 0; i &amp;lt; markers.length; i++) {
	var m = markers[i];
	var marker = L.marker([m.lat, m.long]).addTo(map);
    marker.bindPopup(m.label);
}
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simplicity I’ve used a simple array in the example, but once you are comfortable using SPARQL you can use it to query remote SPARQL endpoints and work directly on the returned results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-more-sparql&quot;&gt;Learning more SPARQL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The queries above are probably the most straightforward (and useful!) queries to learn to get started with SPARQL and so this is where we’ll leave it for our Linked Data 101 series. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any data querying language there’s various levels you may want to take your SPARQL skills up to. A good place to start is our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/01/18/linked-data-webinars-season-2.html&quot;&gt;free 1 hour SPARQL 101 webinar&lt;/a&gt; - the next one is being held on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/webinar-sparql-101-tickets-20857308772&quot; title=&quot;Register for our free SPARQL webinar&quot;&gt;March 10th&lt;/a&gt;. As always &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tags/sparql/&quot;&gt;look our for posts&lt;/a&gt; right here on the blog!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;well text-center&quot;&gt;This article is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tags/ld101-series/&quot;&gt;Linked Data 101 series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/02/29/linked-data-101-querying.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://networkedplanet.com/blog/2016/02/29/linked-data-101-querying.html</guid>
        
        <category>LD101 series</category>
        
        <category>linked data</category>
        
        <category>sparql</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
